<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A present for servants, from their ministers, masters, or other friends, especially in country parishes. Licensed, Jan. 20. 1692.</title>
            <author>Mayo, Richard, 1631?-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50469</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1529</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214162</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826371</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826371</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30773</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50469)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30773)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1764:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A present for servants, from their ministers, masters, or other friends, especially in country parishes. Licensed, Jan. 20. 1692.</title>
                  <author>Mayo, Richard, 1631?-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T. Warren, for Nath. Ranew at the King's Arms in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Richard Mayo.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30773:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PRESENT FOR SERVANTS, From their <hi>Miniſters, Maſters,</hi> OR Other Friends, Eſpecially in Country Pariſhes.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. vii. 24.</hi>
               </bibl> Brethren, let every man, wherein he is called, therein abide with God.</q>
            <p>Licenſed, <hi>Jan.</hi> 20. 1692.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Warren,</hi> for <hi>Nath. Ranew</hi> at the <hi>King's Arms</hi> in <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30773:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30773:2"/>
            <head>TO All Maſters of Families in the Pariſh of <hi>Great Kimbel,</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Grace, Mercy, and Peace, from God our Father, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving deſign'd to write ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the uſe of your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, I could not do better than to put the little Book into your Hands, to whom God has committed the Charge of them; and I have herein the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Example, even of God himſelf, who gives firſt his Commands to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Families, to be by them handed down to all in their Houſes: as, for
<pb facs="tcp:30773:3"/>inſtance, in the great Commandment about the Sabbath, he does not ſpeak to Servants immediately, but makes their Maſters the truſtees of his Will, ſaying, <hi>thou ſhalt do no manner of work, neither thou — nor thy Man-Servant, nor thy Maid-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> implying that <hi>they</hi> muſt cauſe them to obſerve the Commandment; and indeed for this cauſe were Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, as well as all other lawful Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or dain'd, that the Salvation, even of the loweſt members thereof, may be the better furthered under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therein. But alas, how little do men think, when they take on them the Government of Families, that God has committed to them a Charge of Souls? if they did, how durſt they take a Charge that they are not able to perform, by reaſon of their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or never mind, by reaſon of their willfulneſs? if you did believe, that every Servant you take into your Houſe, will add to the dreadfulneſs of your account, if he periſheth through
<pb facs="tcp:30773:3"/>your fault and negligence, could you then be ſo indifferent in your choice of them, as too many be? I remember, <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>His eyes were upon the faithful in the land, that they might ſerve him,</hi> Pſal. <hi>101.6.</hi> but we have Maſters that chuſe Servants as they do their Horſes, if they be ſtrong and able for their work, they mind no more, though you would not bring in a ſcabbed Sheep into your Flock: yet are there not that bring in drunken, ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Servants, with the plague of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs upon them into their Houſes, and lay the infected Wretches with their dear Children and other Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants? Can you as eaſily perform your duty towards obſtinate ſtubborn Servants, as towards thoſe which are good, or at leaſt pliable and willing to be inſtructed and admoniſhed? Is not ſo great a Bleſſing or Curſe, as a good or bad Servant will prove to your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, enough to make you pour out one Prayer for God to direct you in the choice? It is hard that you cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb facs="tcp:30773:4"/>into the Education that they have formerly had, or at leaſt into their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent inclinations to good or evil. Do not lightly take into your Families <hi>a Companion of Fools,</hi> whoſe cuſtoms and habits of ſin have been viſible in their former Converſations, unleſs you have good evidence or ground for hope of their reformation. But the miſery again of it is, when Maſters are as bad as the Servants: He cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after the Godly diſpoſition of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that is about to bring them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a cold Prayerleſs Family; nor can He ask them whether they are willing to be inſtructed, who is himſelf ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that He cannot, or ſo careleſs that He never intends to inſtruct them. But <hi>I am perſwaded better things</hi> of ſome of you, <hi>and things that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company Salvation.</hi> And He that is devoted to God himſelf will engage for his Family too, as Joſhua, <hi>Ch. 24.15. As for me and my houſe, I will ſerve the Lord.</hi> God himſelf gives teſtimony of <hi>Abraham, I know him
<pb facs="tcp:30773:4"/>that He will command his — Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold after him.</hi> Chriſtian Families are frequently called <hi>Churches</hi> for the worſhip of God perform'd therein. Every Maſter is <hi>a Prieſt</hi> in his own Family, and I have often thought his obligation to teach and govern his Servants, is much greater than that of a Miniſter to any particular Family in his Charge. You have an opportunity to know their tempers and temptations, that we have not, and by your nearneſs to them, can take every Servant by himſelf, and deal with him as his caſe requires: by your conſtant continuance with them: and having the power of rewards and puniſhments in your hands, you may more eaſily perform your duty towards them, if you have hearts to it. I know you are counted Good Maſters in the places where you dwell; and I cannot ſay the contrary as to outward things, for ought I know, the moſt of you (if not all) <hi>give unto your Servants that which is juſt and equal,</hi> in neceſſary proviſion, both in health and ſickneſs,
<pb facs="tcp:30773:5"/>in faithful diſcharge of your Contracts in their Wages or Salary, in prudent ordering of their work and buſineſs. And it is not the hard labour of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants that I pity them for, ſo that they are not unneceſſarily expos'd to cold or wet, that may endanger their health; or ſo tyred with the World as to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for Family, or ſecret Prayer, or other duties. For indeed, it is for the Servants <hi>Souls</hi> that I am pleading with you. There is not any poor Boy or Girl that you keep, but has a Soul as pretious as Lords and Ladies, and coſt as dear a price. What have you done for the Souls of them that are under your Roof? Let Conſcience ſpeak, if you ſhould give your Servants no meat and drink, all the Country would cry ſhame on you; but is it not a worſe ſhame and greater Cruelty to ſtarve their Souls? Do you keep Servants with rational Souls, only like your Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to eat, and to drink, and to work? If any of you are not able to inſtruct them, be deeply humbled preſently, and
<pb facs="tcp:30773:5"/>get others to inſtruct them. Ought you not to have required their attendances on publick Catechizing, and their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion thereunto? I am ſure the Church lays no leſs a penalty than Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication upon you if you refuſe; and is not your inſtructing them the way to increaſe in knowledge your ſelves? What if the poor ignorant Servants, that you made part of your Houſhold, ſhould follow you from place to place, from Houſe to Field, and cry after you to inſtruct them? What if they ſhould tell you with many tears, that they are likely to <hi>die without knowledge,</hi> and that they are convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that <hi>Chriſt is coming in flaming fire to take vengeance on them that know not God</hi>— Would you not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them? And if you ſay, but my Servants have no ſuch ſenſe, no ſuch deſire: Why then, are they not the more miſerable? Have they not the greater need? And does not their caſe cry as loud for pity, as their voice can do? Have you no bowels of compaſſion,
<pb facs="tcp:30773:6"/>on periſhing Souls? If not, at leaſt have pity on your own, and let not their blood be on your heads. Family-Duties, and Inſtruction (if carefully minded) would have prevented much of that diſorder that is in almoſt all Pariſhes, which now is not ſo eaſily cur'd; but it requires all your care and diligence to reſtrain that wickedneſs, which igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance has caus'd. What ſaith the Law? Deut. <hi>22.8. When thou buildeſt a new houſe, thou ſhalt make a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement upon the roof, that thou bring not blood upon thy houſe, if any fall from thence.</hi> Family-Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Prayer, Reading, ſinging Pſalms, repetition of Sermons, Catechizing of Servants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are like ſo many Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or <hi>Battlements</hi> on one ſide; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, Reproofs, Corrections, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints from ſin, are Rayls, or <hi>Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements</hi> on the other; and if you ſet not theſe <hi>Battlements</hi> on your Roof, woe be to you, if any fall from thence; and if you ſay, I do not puſh them down, I do not force them, or require
<pb facs="tcp:30773:6"/>them to take ſuch courſes, I would not have them fall. Nay, but this is not enough, you muſt ſet <hi>Battlements,</hi> to prevent their ruining themſelves: If you ſay further, but if I do ſet <hi>Battle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> they may climb over them, and do what I can, will run on to their deſtruction; why then, <hi>their blood will be on their own heads,</hi> and you have delivered <hi>your houſe</hi> from the guilt thereof. By all this you may ſee to how little purpoſe your complaint of wicked Servants has been. When your own Purſe is touch'd by unfaithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, you feel it: You might have known it before, when you ſaw how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe they were to knowledge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that they that were not faithful to God, were not like to be faithful to you; that if you ſuffer'd them to haunt evil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and break the Sabbath, and to live in riotous Courſes; that theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies would call for Money, and where ſhould they have it but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauding you: And if your grief be indeed for the ſin of your Servants a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:30773:7"/>God, I beſeech you look inward; it may be, your ſelves were Servants once, and you liv'd in careleſſneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and unfaithfulneſs toward your Maſters, and now God is <hi>viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſin</hi> upon you: And what comfort can you hope for in your Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, till that guilt be remov'd? And if you are in earneſt, why are you as indifferent about the Servants you chuſe, ſince you have had this experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their wickedneſs, as you were before? Nay, why after trial of their obſtinacy, do you not rid your hands of them? You know <hi>David</hi>'s reſolution, Pſal. <hi>101.7. He that worketh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit ſhall not dwell in my houſe, he that telleth lies ſhall not tarry in my ſight.</hi> But if any keep a debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſon, a Drunkard, prophane Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, obſtinate againſt God, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for a ſecond Year, becauſe it may be, he is ſtrong and able to do his work, I <hi>note that Man</hi> (as there are <hi>noted</hi> Families in the Apoſtles ſenſe, <hi>2 Theſ. 3.14.) and</hi> aſſuredly your ſin will
<pb facs="tcp:30773:7"/>find you out. But if you will be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for God, and againſt ſin in your Families, how much may ſome of you do towards the promoting Religion in the Countrey, and what a Colony of young. perſons may from time to time go out of your houſes, to bear up the Name of Chriſt in the places where they dwell? What <hi>a bleſſing of the Lord will be within your Tabernacle?</hi> What comfort in your Relations? What joy in Afflictions, and even Death it ſelf? Your <hi>Houſe ſhall be built by Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and eſtabliſhed by Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> Prov. <hi>24.3.</hi> that this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Book may ſomething promote this main deſign of Family-Godlineſs, is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Unworthy Miniſter, and Servant for Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Richard Mayo.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:30773:8"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>PREFACE.</label>
MAſters of Families have a Charge of Souls. Their Care in chuſing Servants, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them, and reſtrain them from ſin. Bleſſing upon Godly Families.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. I.</label>
The Kind of Servants treated of. The Providence of God in appointing the Servant's Calling; the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it, not againſt Chriſtian Liberty.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. II.</label>
The Slavery of Souls by Nature. Of the Servants entring into the Service of Chriſt by ſolemn covenanting with him; their Carriage in that Service. Advantage of a Time of
<pb facs="tcp:30773:8"/>Youth, the Dreadfulneſs of the neglect of that Seaſon: Sins of Youth. Death-bed Repentance. What Families Servants ſhould chuſe. Of doing what they do unto the Lord.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. III.</label>
The Servant's Reverence to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Of Fidelity to them, Of Eye-Service, Of cheating and defraud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Of Obedience in harſh and unpleaſant things. Of doing what they do heartily. Not anſwering again.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
Of Servants tempting each other to ſin. Sinful Familiarity of Servants of different Sexes. Of reproving and warning the unruly. Of Holy Conference. Of Servants helping each other, in their Work, and in Soul-Affairs.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:30773:9"/>
                  <label>CHAP. V.</label>
The careleſs Ignorance of ſome Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and danger of it. Of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing, and Servants ſubmitting thereunto, and how. Of fervent Prayer for Knowledge. Of Knowing Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
The Hardſhips of Servants. Danger and Cure of Diſcontent. The Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of Servants. The miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Condition of Slaves in other Parts. Of the Temptations of <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of State</hi> in Great Places. Inconveniences of the Condition of poor Houſe-Keepers, the worſt Slavery of all. The Freedom of Godly Servants. The Glorious Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Sons of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VII.</label>
Servants Want of Time. How Godly Servants gain Time. How Wicked Servants waſte their Time. Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of it. Of the Lord's Day, and how Servants muſt improve it.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30773:9"/>
            <head>A PRESENT FOR SERVANTS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Kinds of Servants, and of the lawfulneſs of the Servants Calling.</head>
               <p>THERE is ſcarce any gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Name of a <hi>Calling,</hi> that contains under it, ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent kinds of Perſons, as this of a <hi>Servant.</hi> Some <hi>Service</hi> being ſo high and honourable, that there is no Subject ſo great, but that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30773:10"/>in being Entitled the King's <hi>Servant,</hi> in the various Offices of his Houſhold; and ſome Service is ſo vile and miſerable, that the pooreſt Perſon in a Free Land is happy in being delivered from it. There are three ſorts of Servants that I ſhall name, tho' it be only for the laſt of them that I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended this Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There are <hi>Servants of State,</hi> that make up the Retinue of Great Men and Nobles, who living in Eaſe, Pleaſure, and Worldly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licacies, have no agreement with thoſe that I am concern'd with, ſave in the bare Name.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There are <hi>Slaves</hi> and <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> ſunk in the loweſt ſtate of miſery in the World, being under the ſole diſpoſal of the uncontrouled Wills [and Luſts] of their [often bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous] Owners. And theſe are ſo either <hi>juſtly,</hi> being condemn'd for ſome Capital Crimes, and in Mercy Repriev'd, and ſpar'd as to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30773:10"/>Life, but deprived of their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and many Comforts of Life; or elſe <hi>unjuſtly,</hi> by a violent Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, or by unrighteous Sales and Contracts. But I leave theſe (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God) to thoſe who are acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their Circumſtances, and Temptations, and have opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to help them in the way to Heaven. And ſhall apply my ſelf to,</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Third ſort of <hi>Servants,</hi> in a ſtate of Life between the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and which are moſt uſual a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, as making up a part of every Family; and they are ſuch as <hi>by reaſon of Poverty, or a meaner condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the World, have voluntarily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelves, by Contract, for a certain time, to the diſpoſal of others, according to the Word of God, and Laws of the Realm:</hi> And this Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is founded upon the Will and Providence of God in theſe two things,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>In eſtabliſhing Property, and thereby a ſeemingly unequal diſtribution
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30773:11"/>of the good things of this Life.</hi> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this the Relation of Maſter and Servant could not ſtand. Prov. 12.7. <hi>The rich ruleth over the poor, and the borrower is Servant to the Lender.</hi> This inequality is not by chance, but by the Soveraign Diſpoſer of the Lord of all, 1 Sam. 2.7. <hi>The Lord maketh poor, and maketh rich.</hi> Perhaps in Innocency (if that ſtate had continu'd) all things might have been in common; the Corn and Trees as free to all, as the Light and Air are now. But to ſuppoſe it ſo with us, is to make a perpetual War, many quarrelling about the ſame thing; as when one Bone is caſt amongſt ſeveral Dogs. And therefore that Community of Goods, which we read of, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.34. was extraordinary, and laſted but a very little while: ſo that now all have a right to the things that they do lawfully poſſeſs, whether by Inheritance, Donation, or as gotten by honeſt labour and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30773:11"/>and as all Laws of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> depend upon this, ſo does this <hi>Relation</hi> of which we are ſpeaking.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His Will and Providence is further ſeen <hi>in rendering all perſons in this inequality of their Conditiöns mutually helpful to each other, yea ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to one another in this lapſed ſtate;</hi> and the beauty and order of God's Government of the World is much to be obſerved, that each ſhall ſtand in need of his Brother's help towards his own convenient ſubſiſtance in the World; that as it is in the <hi>natural</hi> (and, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, in the <hi>myſtical</hi>) ſo it is in the <hi>political</hi> Body, 1 Cor. 12.21, 22. <hi>The eye cannot ſay to the hand, I have no need of thee; nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the head to the feet, I have no need of you; nay much more thoſe members of the body which ſeem to be more feeble, are neceſſary.</hi> The <hi>Rich</hi> cannot ſay to the <hi>Poor, We have no need of you.</hi> For whence then will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30773:12"/>they have their Servants? And how can they miſs the help which they daily receive by them? As the <hi>Hands</hi> need the <hi>Head</hi> for Guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Direction, ſo does the <hi>Head</hi> need the <hi>Hands</hi> for Work and Service. And indeed by this means, the ſeeming inequality in the diſtribution of worldly things is made up. That as it is <hi>in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Charity,</hi> as the Apoſtle doth eſtabliſh it, <hi>in an equality, that your abundance may be a ſupply for their want, that their abundance may alſo be a ſupply for your want, that there may be equality. As it is written, he that gathered much had nothing over, and he that gathered little had no lack,</hi> 2 Cor. 8.14, 15. Even juſt thus it is <hi>in matter of juſtice; in an equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> that your Money, Wages, and Proviſion may <hi>be a ſupply</hi> for their indigency, and their Work and Service <hi>a ſupply</hi> for your ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to diſcharge your buſineſs without them; and ſo all things
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30773:12"/>are ſet right, one <hi>has nothing over,</hi> and the other <hi>has no lack.</hi> And perhaps amongſt the variety <hi>of places,</hi> no Servants are more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary than thoſe in Country-Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; others wear finer Liveries, feed higher, and lie eaſier: But the labour of the Country Servant is of moſt excellent and general uſe: <hi>The profit of the Earth is for all, the King himſelf is ſerv'd of the field,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 5.9. and tho' he muſt rub through many hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, yet he may comfort himſelf in this, that the moſt drudging part of his Service is of neceſſity to the Common-wealth: and when ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Callings are apparently unlawful, and not a few exceeding doubtful; The Servant's Calling, if not abus'd, is unqueſtionably lawful. It is true, there is a Text that ſeems to oppoſe the Servants Calling, and the lawfulneſs thereof; it is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23. <hi>You are bought with the price, be ye not the Servants
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30773:13"/>of Men.</hi> With which agree our Lord's Word, <hi>Call no Man Maſter upon Earth;</hi> and poſſible it is, that in the Apoſtles Days, ſome hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>liberty</hi> purchaſed by Chriſt; might begin to caſt off their <hi>Service,</hi> eſpecially to unbelieving <hi>Maſters:</hi> and therefore we find the Apoſtles <hi>Paul, Peter,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> ſo frequently calling <hi>Servants</hi> to their duty, and inſtructing them better in it. And though we are told, that Believers <hi>are all one in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Gal. 3, 28. Yet it muſt be underſtood of <hi>the ſoul, or inner man,</hi> and of <hi>the means of grace,</hi> in order to the Salvation thereof; for as to the <hi>outward Man,</hi> they are ſtill <hi>bond and free,</hi> and abide <hi>Maſter,</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> ſtill. And ſo when he bids them to be no more <hi>Servants of Men,</hi> he has reſpect to the inner Man, or Conſcience, which none can Command but God. And tho our Lord has purchaſed a <hi>liberty</hi> for our <hi>Bodies,</hi> as well as for our
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30773:13"/>
                  <hi>Souls;</hi> yet we attain but to the firſt-fruits of it now: There remains a <hi>Reſt</hi> to be enjoy'd after Death, <hi>then the weary are at reſt</hi>— ſaith <hi>Job, and the Servant is free from his Maſter.</hi> But we are not now freed from all Moleſtations, Troubles and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies in any ſtate, and ſo not from that of <hi>Service,</hi> when called thereunto. I ſhall therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſet down,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>The Duties of Servants,</hi> and how they may be beſt perform'd. And then,</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>The Temptations, and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences of their Calling,</hi> and how they may beſt be prevented, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy'd by them.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Duty of Servants <hi>[1]</hi> towards GOD.</head>
               <p>THERE is ſuch a comprehenſive fulneſs in Scripture, in which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30773:14"/>
                  <hi>the Commandments are exceeding broad,</hi> that there is no Caſe, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or Relation, in which the People of God can be or ſtand, but there is ſomething in the word that is ſuited thereunto. There are none ſo high, but the Word is above them; and none ſo low, but the Word condeſcends to them, and ſpeaks to their ſtate and caſe. <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> may be overlook'd by the World, but they are directed by the Word: And from that Word I ſhall endeavour to ſpeak to <hi>the Duty</hi> of Servants, under theſe three Heads.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Their Duty towards <hi>God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Their Duty towards <hi>their Maſters.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Their Duty towards their <hi>Fellow-Servants,</hi> in the Family and Neighbourhood.</item>
               </list>
               <p>As to the former; their <hi>Duty towards God,</hi> muſt firſt be minded, as the foundation of their <hi>Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Men.</hi> I have no hopes to do
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30773:14"/>you good, unleſs, I can prevail with you in theſe matters of the higheſt concern.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) <hi>That you would engage your ſelves in the Service of God,</hi> and be his Servants in the firſt place. You are already his Servants at large, and by outward profeſſion: You have taken his <hi>Earneſt,</hi> and worn his <hi>Livery,</hi> upon your being Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. It hath been no ſtrange thing in the Church of God, to have In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants own'd by God to <hi>be his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> viz. by an external Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Profeſſion: They are called ſo, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.41, 42. and ſince this you have born <hi>his Name,</hi> and Liv'd in his Houſe, and eat of his Bread, and pretended to his Wages, you have a Work to do, and ſhall at laſt be called to a Reckoning, when the Great Maſter comes; but alas, alas! How many are there, that are the <hi>Servants of Chriſt</hi> in Name, but really <hi>the Servants of Sin</hi> all the time? For know you not, <hi>His Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30773:15"/>you are whom you obey,</hi> Rom. 6.16. <hi>Jeſus ſaith unto them, Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, He that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth ſin, is the Servant of ſin,</hi> Job 8.34. <hi>You your ſelves were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fooliſh— ſerving divers Luſts and Pleaſures,</hi> Tit. 3.3. Rom. 6.17, 20. 2 Pet. 2.19. You are by nature <hi>Slaves,</hi> in your nobleſt part, to the vileſt of Creatures, in the baſeſt drudgery. How has the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil made you ſerve blindfold, in Bonds and Chains? If you are once made ſenſible of your caſe, you would ſigh and groan to be ſet at liberty, you would be very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive to find out a better place, you would long to be directed to ſome better Service. And if ſo, I come to give you notice to my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; who tho' he wants not you, nor any Servant that he has, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry willing to entertain you in his Service. It is an honourable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and a profitable Service, there is no ſuch Maſter, no ſuch
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30773:15"/>Wages to be had any where elſe. Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt offers to ſtand in many near relations to you, and you that know what it is to go to Service, ſhould know upon what terms you may become the Servants of Chriſt. See then,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That you give up your ſelves to God and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt by a ſolemn Covenant and Contract.</hi> It is by Contract that you are Servants in the places where you live, you knew what you did when you were hir'd, upon what terms you took the Earneſt: Now, <hi>Why ſtand you all the day idle?</hi> Why are your Souls ſo long out of the Service of ſo great, ſo good a Maſter? Say not, <hi>No Man has hir'd us:</hi> I this Day call and invite you into the Family of God, <hi>the Houſhold of Faith.</hi> Will you accept of his terms, and conſent to the Covenant? He ſtands not with you upon the rigorous terms of the Covenant of Works; He has admitted a Surety, who has
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30773:16"/>ſatisfy'd the Demands of Juſtice, and purchas'd moſt excellent terms of Grace for you: And now <hi>what does the Lord thy God require of thee?</hi> He expects that you renounce your former Maſters. He will have all his Servants be <hi>for him, and not for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; no Man can ſerve two Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</hi> He expects that you ſhould <hi>reverence his Son,</hi> that being ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom'd from your Slavery, and <hi>bought with the price,</hi> you ſhould depend on his Merits, and ſubmit to his Will; and <hi>ſerve him in your Souls and Bodies which are his.</hi> Now <hi>who is He that engageth his heart to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to God?</hi> Have you conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his terms, <hi>You muſt for ſake your Father's Houſe, and your own People:</hi> The <hi>divers Luſts and Pleaſures</hi> which you formerly <hi>ſerved,</hi> muſt be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely and eternally abandoned: you muſt renounce your vain Confiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſubmit to his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, you muſt deny your own Wills, and ſtoop to his Word;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30773:16"/>you muſt give up your Selves, Souls, and Bodies to be rul'd by him, as ever you hope to be ſav'd by him. Do you now like his terms? If you ſay, No, <hi>as the Lord liveth,</hi> He will come down no lower: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>yield your ſelves unto the Lord, as you have yielded your members Servants of iniquity unto iniquity; ſo now, yield your members Servants of righteouſneſs, unto holineſs.</hi> I know it muſt be the <hi>Finger of God</hi> that muſt turn about your Hearts, and make you willing to his Contract: And who knows but it may be <hi>the day of his power</hi> to ſome poor Souls? Wherefore ponder upon your ſtate by nature, till you are deeply affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with your former ſlavery; let the making of this Contract be look'd upon, as the moſt ſolemn tranſaction of your Lives: Get into a corner and <hi>count the coſt.</hi> He ſees you as he did <hi>Nathanael,</hi> as ſome think, about the ſame work <hi>under the Fig-tree.</hi> Reckon upon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30773:17"/>
                  <hi>bearing the burden and heat of the day,</hi> upon ſtorms and many a cold blaſt in your Faces; beg as for your Lives, the aſſiſtance of his Spirit, and let each of you <hi>take to himſelf words, and ſay, Other Lords have had Dominion over me, but I am thy Servant, truly I am thy Servant— I put my ſelf under the wings of the God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>I will never be the World's again; nor Sin's, nor</hi> Satan's <hi>any more: I am thine, and thou art mine.</hi> Amen, <hi>And the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſay ſo too.</hi> Being thus hired, you muſt ſee then,</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That you diligently apply your ſelves to know and do the will of your Maſter.</hi> Being bound you muſt obey, <hi>having open'd your mouths un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, you cannot go back.</hi> You are in for your Lives, yea for ever and ever: You muſt have your <hi>ear bor'd</hi> to the Poſts of the Door, and ſay, <hi>I love my Maſter, and will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver depart from him:</hi> You muſt chiefly delight in the inward part
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30773:17"/>of your work, but baulk no duty for any difficulty or danger that you may meet with therein: You muſt not be quarreling with your Fellow-Servants, when you ſhould be at work; but do all you do as approving your ſelves to the eye of your Maſter: You muſt depend on the ſtrength of Chriſt in all the Service you perform: and when you have done all, muſt count your ſelves <hi>unprofitable Servants,</hi> and look only to his Grace and Merits for Pardon and Acceptance. Nor ſhall you ever ſay, that He is <hi>a hard Maſter, reaping where he did not ſow, and gathering where he did not ſtrow:</hi> You ſhall have no occaſion to liken him to the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Task-Maſters, that required Brick, but gave no Straw: He is neither Tyrannical in his Commands, nor niggardly in his Encouragements: He is not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to be pleaſed, nor will he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways chide: He ſtands not upon legal perfection, but admits of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30773:18"/>and Sincerity: He offers his aſſiſtance, that you may <hi>do all through Chriſt ſtrengthening you:</hi> He allows you to <hi>look to the recompence of reward,</hi> that you may go the more chearfully on, as thoſe <hi>that know that your labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) The next Duty of Servants <hi>is to improve the time of youth and ſtrength.</hi> The uſual time of going to Service, is in the younger years; in that Age only are they thought fit for the Service of Men: Oh let not the main work then be neglected in it!</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe I commend to Servants theſe two Conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>How advantageous a time the youthful Age is,</hi> and what pity it is ſo free a time ſhould be loſt, an Age in which God uſually lays hold on the hearts of thoſe, whom he brings home to himſelf, and in which Converſion is much eaſier, like the bending of a tender Twig,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30773:18"/>than when ſome old knotty Root is to be cleav'd, which muſt have many a Blow; and indeed as <hi>every thing is beautiful in its ſeaſon,</hi> ſo how lovely is early Piety? when the Young Man in the Goſpel had but ſome good Inclinations, it is ſaid, <hi>Jeſus lov'd him.</hi> How ſtrong are ſuch like to be and grow in Grace, when like a Plant early ſet, it has time to take Root? How fruitful will they prove, when <hi>they ſhall ſtill bring forth fruit</hi> even <hi>to old Age?</hi> What uſeful, experimental Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians do ſuch prove, who have had a long time to taſt the ſweetneſs of the ways of Chriſt, that they early choſe? None ever repented at laſt that they came in to Chriſt too ſoon: on the contrary, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of the Holy Ghoſt ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them, that they have not loſt their Pleaſures, but chang'd them; left ſenſual Tranſitory Delights for ſuch as are Spiritual and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:30773:19"/>2. On the other ſide, <hi>How dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful the neglect of the time of youth will prove:</hi> how woful the hazard, and how certain the damage. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted Youth is as full of ſin, as <hi>Job</hi>'s Body was of ſores. We read of <hi>youthful luſts,</hi> the <hi>iniquities of our youth,</hi> which corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in that Age is ſtrongly incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to. How long a Vacation is there uſually from God and Duty! What <hi>fooliſh talking and jeſting, which is not convenient?</hi> Is there not (if not Oaths and Execrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet) abominable lying in the Tongue? How ſad is it to ſee, the Pride and Vanity, Diſobedience to Parents, Contempt of Advice, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifying of the Miniſters and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt, and above all, the prevailing Love of Pleaſures, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Pleaſures, or at leaſt of ill Report, reigning amongſt Youth at this day! if through Grace they be awakened in their elder Years (which is the beſt that can be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30773:19"/>thought of) yet how bitter will theſe youthful Sins be to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, when they <hi>are made to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the iniquities of their youth?</hi> they will quickly <hi>receive of the Lord double for all their ſins,</hi> i.e. dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and triply more of horrour, than ever they found of ſweetneſs in them. But alas, it is very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſo well with them who have loſt their Youth in Sin. <hi>Can the Aethiopian change his skin, or the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard his ſpot?</hi> &amp;c. How impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble almoſt to reclaim them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if they ſpent their Youth in Vanity under the Goſpel! Life is uncertain, and you have no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to live a day, and if you live till Age, alas, how ſoon will it come? <hi>the time in which you will ſay, We have no pleaſure in it.</hi> How little is the Sinner, that has miſs'd his time, and grown grey in ſin, acquainted with the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the work, which he has ſo fooliſhly delayed! Do you think
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30773:20"/>in your Conſciences, That <hi>all</hi> which you have ſo frequently heard of Converſion and Regeneration, <hi>all</hi> about a Life of Self-denyal, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Humility, and Contempt of this World, is no more than to ſay, <hi>Lord, have mercy upon me,</hi> when you are ſick, or to ſend for the Miniſter to pray by you? Can the Work that requires the beſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, the greateſt Strength and Compoſedneſs of mind, and Retiredneſs from the World, be performed at laſt, when you have ſpent your Youth and Strength in Ignorance and Obſtinacy, and come to be full of Pains of Body, and Agonies of Mind, and tyred with Company in Sickneſs, and the over-officious Love of Friends as careleſs as your ſelves? I know the Inſtance of the Thief upon the Croſs is urged for a putting off Repentance to the laſt. But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it were granted, That there was no Work begun on his Soul,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30773:20"/>before thoſe laſt hours, yet how many thouſands have miſcarried by ſuch Delays, to one ſingle Inſtance of a Man that eſcapd! Is not one to ſo many thouſands bgreat Odds, and he brought in at ſuch an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſeaſon, as never was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, nor ever will be again? It was in a time when all things were carried in a miraculous way; the <hi>Sun was darkned, the Rocks ſplit, the Temple-veil rent, the Earth ſhook, and the Graves opened,</hi> and a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner converted at the laſt. Our Lord was <hi>ſpoiling Principalities and Powers,</hi> and as Captains ſnatch a Standard from the Enemy, as a token of Victory; ſo did our Lord reſcue this Soul out of the hands of Satan, as a Standard gain'd to <hi>make a Shew of it openly, triumphing</hi> thereby <hi>over Satan in his Croſs.</hi> And how eaſily may this Inſtance be retorted on the careleſs Waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of their Youth, that the Thief on the Croſs came in at the firſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30773:21"/>Call, and, for ought appears to us, had never one Goſpel-Invitation before? Did he ever deſpiſe the offers of Grace from Year to Year as you have done? What a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence does this make, that you have had duving your time of Youth and Vanity, <hi>Line upon Line, Precept upon Precept,</hi> and have <hi>grieved, quenched, tempted, vexed, reſiſted,</hi> and even <hi>done deſpight to the ſpirit of Grace?</hi> And do you think to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the free influences of the Spirit, when you have miſs'd your time, and he ſaith, <hi>He will laugh at your Calamity, and mock when your fear cometh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">(3.) The laſt thing I ſhall name in the Servants Duty towards God, is <hi>to do what they do in their places, as to the Lord, and not unto Men,</hi> Col. 3.23. <hi>Whatever you do in word or deed, do all in the Name of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> as eyeing the Image of his Authority in thoſe that God has ſet over you, <hi>for you ſerve the Lord Chriſt.</hi> In order to this,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:30773:21"/>1. <hi>See that in the entrance into Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or any new Place, you mind chiefly, where you may have the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt advantages for your Souls.</hi> Let not the eaſieſt work, or moſt wages, be the main thing in your Eye, in the places where you go. Do not run into an infected place for ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle outward advantage: Do not chuſe to live in a Pariſh where there is no preaching Miniſtry, nor in a Family where there is no worſhip of God; eſpecially if the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Members of the Family be notoriouſly prophane, ſhun ſuch a Houſe as you would one in which the plague were broke out. And if God has caſt your Lot into a Godly Family, eſteem it as a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial favour, and remember to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove <hi>the price put into your hands.</hi> It was a ſtartling Speech of a holy Miniſter to a Maid Servant, and prov'd of great uſe to her,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Machin</hi> in vit.</note> when obſerving how God had plac'd her in a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30773:22"/>Family, He told her, <hi>That if ſhe went to Hell out of that Family, ſhe would have a deep place there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That in doing the work of your Earthly Maſters, you ſeek the ſtrength, and aim at the glory of your heavenly Maſter.</hi> Not to mention the Lord's Day as yet, you muſt every day conſcientiouſly beg a bleſſing upon your work, and commit your Souls, Bodies, Relations, and lawful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings into the hands of God by Faith and Prayer: you partake of the Mercies of the Family, and therefore you muſt pray down a Bleſſing upon it. You remember Good <hi>Eleazar,</hi> Gen. 24.12. <hi>O Lord God of my Maſter</hi> Abraham, I <hi>pray thee ſend me good ſpeed this day, and ſhew kindneſs to my Maſter</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Prayer is the means to know your duty in your Service, and to be able to perform it; by this means you may have the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of your Maſters, and of the truth it ſelf, which <hi>Jacob</hi> had of his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30773:22"/>Maſter <hi>Laban,</hi> Gen. 30.27. <hi>I have learned by experience, that the Lord hath bleſſed me for thy ſake.</hi> And this leads me to the ſecond Part of the Servants Duty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The Servants Duty <hi>[2.]</hi> towards their Maſters.</head>
               <p>HE is the good Chriſtian that is good in the place and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherein God has ſet him, and that is the Religious Servant, who out of a Principle of love to God, and in obedience to his Command, does perform his duty to them to whom God has ſubjected him.</p>
               <p>Your Duty therefore towards your Maſters conſiſts, 1. <hi>In the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend ſubjection of mind, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectful honour that your place requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. Let as many Servants as are under the Yoke, count their Maſters
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30773:23"/>worthy of all honour, that the name of Chriſt, and his Doctrine, be not bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphem'd,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.1, 2. this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Apoſtle is the more remarkable, becauſe it is ſpoken to them that had Infidel Maſters: and if yours be Unbelievers, wicked Perſons, without ſo much as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, your Duty is more difficult; it is hard to honour a Fool, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence one that you frequently ſee in his Vomit of Drunkenneſs, or venom of Malice and Paſſion. But yet their Authority they have from God, and you muſt reverence the Image of God's Dominion in them, leſt you cauſe the <hi>name of Chriſt to be blaſphem'd,</hi> and leſt you give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to the wicked Man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach Religion, and to ſay, <hi>Theſe are your Profeſſours, your Religious Servants, ay, they are all alike.</hi> And if ſo be that God has ſubjected you to thoſe that are ſerious and Godly, you muſt honour them the more. So ſaith the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>ver.</hi> 3.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30773:23"/>
                  <hi>and they that have believing maſters let them not deſpiſe them, becauſe they are Brethren, but rather do them ſervice becauſe they are faithful and beloved, partakers of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</hi> Be not you like thoſe inſolent Youths that ſet light by their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, either before their faces or behind their backs. God has not ſet you as Companions with your Maſters, nor does he allow of a ſawcy Carriage in their preſence, nor to talk diſreſpectfully of them, or of their Imperfections in their abſence. The more careful they are to inſtruct, reprove, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain you from ſin and vanity, the more do you prize them, and bleſs God for them. Be as ready (or more) to be catechized, exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and directed about your Souls, as about any buſineſs that you are employ'd about.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Your Duty lies <hi>in a Religious faithfulneſs, and conſtant fidelity, in all that you undertake.</hi> When you
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30773:24"/>hired your ſelves, you ſold your <hi>time</hi> and labour to your Maſters, all but what God and nature more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately requires to be reſerv'd: and beſides the ſin againſt God in idleneſs, you defraud your Maſter, if you idle away an hour, that ſhould be employ'd in his buſineſs. And to delay his Meſſages, put off his work to others; to ſlubber over his work, or leave it half undone, is to rob your Maſter of the Wages that is due for the work, which you ſhould have done accordingly, but did not. This is the <hi>Eye-Service,</hi> which the Apoſtle condemns, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.22. when Hypocritically you ſeem earneſt in his work when his Eye is upon you, but loyter away your time when he has turn'd his back. They that are unfaithful in their Maſter's work, will not ('tis to be fear'd) make much Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of defrauding him in his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</hi> How quickly does the Devil teach an ungodly Servant to make
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30773:24"/>bold with his Maſter's Money, in buying or ſelling, and to excuſe it by the ſecrecy, or ſmalneſs of the matter; till they who made no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to trample on God's Law for a Peny, came afterwards to Pounds and higher Robberies. And here let me beg of Servants to take heed of Ale-Houſes, Gaming-Houſes, places of Drunkenneſs or Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of loving Cards and Dice, or ſitting up to unſeaſonable hours at ſuch Vanities: ſuch will need much Money to play away and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot away, and then how ſtrong is the temptation to keep back, or convey away part of the Money, that you ſold the Goods for! if you have any of theſe Devices, know, It is a downright Theft, and if it be but a Peny, you know not where it will ſtop. They that take a little, when the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation is ſtrong will venture up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a great deal; and they that rob their Maſter to day, will rob o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30773:25"/>to morrow. And how ſad and bitter a Caſe muſt this prove, when the beſt that can be hop'd for, is a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of your Theft, full of ſorrow and ſhame, and the <hi>reſtitution</hi> of every farthing, to the utmoſt of your power; without which there can be no Repentance, and ſo no Salvation. And if this be not done, your Thefts in your Service will be like Moths in your Goods, when you come to get ſomething of your own: <hi>of your own</hi> did I ſay? Yea, till you have made reſtitution, you do not eat your <hi>own bread;</hi> and 'tis not your giving part of your ill-gotten Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the poor, that will prevent the horrour of Conſcience at laſt. <hi>God hates robbery for burnt-offering.</hi> I'll add but one Inſtance more under this Head, which is the Perfidiouſneſs of Servants in any <hi>Truſt</hi> committed to them. Like the unjuſt Steward, that when there was owing his Maſter <hi>an hundred
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30773:25"/>meaſures of wheat,</hi> order'd them to <hi>take their bill and write four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore.</hi> And if you ſhould ſay, but did not the <hi>Lord commend the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt ſteward?</hi> Yes, for his wiſdom, not for his cheating his Maſter. It is a Parable, and we muſt mind the ſcope of it, which is to ſhew us a pattern of foreſight; how we ſhould ſecure <hi>a better habitation,</hi> when theſe Tabernacles fail, as this wicked Servant look'd about him what ſhould become of him, when his Maſter turn'd him out. Another manner of Servant was <hi>Jacob,</hi> who had a hard Service in the Summers Heat, and Winters Froſts for twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years, yet could ſay, Gen. 30.33. <hi>My righteouſneſs ſhall anſwer for me</hi>— and if it be ſaid, Did not <hi>Jacob</hi> play faſt and looſe with his Maſter, in laying the Rods in the watering Troughs? I ſuppoſe not; the effect being not natural, but by a Special Providence, and therefore we find the fact not by his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30773:26"/>but by God's appointment in a Dream, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.10. who thus <hi>gave away</hi> what was <hi>Laban</hi>'s to <hi>Jacob.</hi> But beyond all Examples is that plain Command, Tit. 2.10. — <hi>Not purloyning, but ſhewing all good fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that they may adorn the Doctrine of God our Saviour in all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Your Duty lies further <hi>in a willing Obedience, and conſcientious hearkning to your Maſter's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</hi> And tho' you muſt not perform your Service <hi>as Men-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers,</hi> Col. 3.22. <hi>i. e.</hi> as meerly ſuch, you muſt pleaſe God chiefly, as the one thing neceſſary, yet in, and under him, the ſame Apoſtle tells you, That your Obedience to your Maſters, lies in doing their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in all that they ſet you about, Tit. 2.9. <hi>Exhort Servants to be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to their Maſters, and to pleaſe them well in all things.</hi> Indeed we read of <hi>a pleaſing Men,</hi> that will not ſtand with our being <hi>the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt:</hi> You therefore ſtill
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30773:26"/>remember, God is their Maſter and yours. And if your earthly Maſter command any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God's Word; as to Lye, or Cheat for his gain, or the like, as you love your Souls, <hi>obey God rather than Men.</hi> But now as to all lawful things, the Command ſtands good, Col. 3.22. <hi>Servants, obey in all things, your Maſters, according to the fleſh</hi>— So that if the things be mean or low, and, as you think, below you, you muſt not nicely ſtand upon your Honour, but ſet about your work; yea tho' the Command be harſh and unpleaſant, you muſt bring down your high Stomach, and ſubmit. So you'll read, 1 Pet. 2.18. <hi>Servants, be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to your Maſters with all fear, not only to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward.</hi> If your Maſter be froward, haſty, difficult to be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and it may be ready to injure you (this is his ſin, and a very great one) yet you muſt perform your
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30773:27"/>Duty to God and him. But you'll ſay, Is there no Remedy for a poor <hi>Servant oppreſs'd</hi> by a Churliſh <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> no way to avoid his Rigour, and unjuſt Severity? Why Yes, He may for the preſent withdraw himſelf prudently to avoid his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's rage; and tho' in caſe of the utmoſt extremity the Servant may obtain the help of the Magiſtrate againſt an unreaſonable Maſter, yet uſually the Apoſtle's Caution is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, for the Servants to forbear all muttering returns, which he calls, Tit. 2.9.— <hi>not anſwering again.</hi> Which is not meant that they muſt refuſe a reſpectful An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Queſtions, when they are ask'd. That is as great a fault on the other ſide (as the Wiſe Man ſaith) <hi>when they underſtand, not to anſwer,</hi> Prov. 29.19. But that they ſhould not thwart and contradict, or by rugged and unmannerly words provoke their Maſter's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt them. On the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30773:27"/>contrary, there is required a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Obedience, called a doing what they do <hi>heartily,</hi> or from the heart, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.23. and if in harſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant things you muſt obey, how are they to blame, that refuſe their Maſters Orders, in the moſt gentle and neceſſary things? That will tell their Maſters <hi>they were not hir'd to be catechiz'd,</hi> or the like. Which is not only an affront to God in the contemning of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances for your Souls, but a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to them whom God has ſet over you. For when you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Servants, it is not only in this or that work that ſuits your hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, as if you were to ſet your Conceits and Wills againſt their Commands; but in all lawful things belonging to your place, whereby you may teſtifie your Obedience to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:30773:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The Duty of Servants <hi>[3.]</hi> towards their Fellow-ſervants in the Family and Neighbourhood.</head>
               <p>THey that are of the ſame Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or ſtate of life in the World, are wont to be counted <hi>Brethren:</hi> and eſpecially when they live near to each other, ſhould moſt entirely love as ſuch. Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety is the great Comfort of Life, and Equality of Condition much adds to the ſweetneſs of it, where there be other higher Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Indeed there is hardly any word ſo much abus'd as that of <hi>Good-Fellowſhip.</hi> Men miſtake the <hi>Order</hi> of it, making it chiefly to reſpect the Body, which is to be minded in ſubordination to the Soul: and no leſs, the <hi>Matter</hi> of it. <hi>Good-Fellowſhip</hi> with them is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30773:28"/>to be amongſt their Cups, at beſt in idle Chat and Vanity. And Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Youth hear it told by ſome grown grey in careleſsneſs, What <hi>love and good neighbourhood</hi> there was, when they had not ſo much <hi>Preaching,</hi> nor ſuch ado a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion. But the Chriſtian Servant has <hi>not ſo learned Chriſt.</hi> There are more noble Ends of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, than careleſs Servants know; ſuch as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Mutual Watchfulneſs,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally over the Souls of each other. It is true, That here Charity muſt begin at home, in a cautious fear of danger to your own Souls, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if your Companions in the Family be none of the beſt. Take heed you be not Tempters of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nor your ſelves tempted by them. Remember the Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſpeaks unto you as unto Children. Prov. 1.10. <hi>My Son, if Sinners entice thee, conſent thou not.</hi> And undue Familiarity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30773:29"/>Servants of different Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in a Family, has had fatal and tragical Effects. How often has Opportunity and Privacy expos'd Men and Maids that live toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Devil's Temptations. And in houſes, where the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have ſet <hi>battlements on the roof,</hi> they have leap'd over into the ditch, (for <hi>a Whore is a deep ditch, and he that is abhorred of the Lord ſhall fall therein,</hi> Prov. 22.14.) How much more are Servants in danger, where they have no warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but wicked Examples; how ſoon do filthy Words, and wanton Dalliances betray them? <hi>He that feareth the Lord ſhall eſcape the ſnare, but the ſinner ſhall be taken in it,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.26. And if they be of the ſame Sex, there is no ſmall danger in a converſe with thoſe that have infectious diſeaſes, and running ſores of prophaneneſs upon them. If they be only in the Neighbourhood, that are thus
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:30773:29"/>infected, it is more eaſie to avoid them. 2 Theſ. 3.6. <hi>Now we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, That you withdraw your ſelves from every brother that walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth diſorderly — Who toucheth pitch and is not defiled? Can any take coals in his boſom and not be burnt?</hi> But if the Plague be in the Houſe where you are, and your Fellow-ſervants Drunkards, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Swearers, Scoffers at Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, your Caſe is the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. How came you into this Hell on Earth, where theſe things are ſuffered? Ought you not to be deeply humbled, That you made no better choice? And upon what terms do you ſtay longer there? You had need have a clear Call, to dwell in a Peſt-houſe. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs while you ſtay in that place, <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thy heart, but ſhalt in any wiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke him, and not ſuffer ſin upon him,</hi> Lev. 19.17. It ſeems with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, you can neither teſtifie
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:30773:30"/>your hatred of their ſins, nor free your ſelves from the imputation of hatred of their Souls. You muſt do it in faithfulneſs to your own Souls, and you know not but you may thereby <hi>gain</hi> theirs. You muſt watch the beſt Opportunity that your nearneſs to them will afford you, to <hi>tell them their fault between them and you alone;</hi> and with plainneſs lay open their ſin before them, <hi>this open rebuke is better than ſecret love.</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue your Duty, if they go on to ſin, unleſs, by ſcoffing Malignity, and Fury, they ſhew themſelves to be <hi>the dogs and ſwine</hi> that you muſt not <hi>throw your pearls before, leſt they turn again and rent you.</hi> And then you can do no more, unleſs by getting others to rebuke them, who by their Authority, may be more likely to prevail, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> brought to his Father his <hi>ſon's evil report.</hi> And if Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence has caſt your lot amongſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:30773:30"/>ſuch as are civil and towardly, your Duty will be more eaſie. They will willingly be warn'd by you, and thankfully take your cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for their Souls good: you will not be tempted ſo much to uſe the words of the firſt Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Am I my Brother's keeper?</hi> but if (not only civil, but) Godly Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants meet in the ſame Houſe or Neighbourhood, they will <hi>agree</hi> together to watch over and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to admoniſh one another. <hi>Two are better than one— for if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow, but wo bo to him that is alone when He falleth, for He hath not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to help him up— and if one prevail againſt him, two ſhall withſtand him, and a threefold cord is not quickly broken,</hi> Eccl. 4.10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By this watchfulneſs over each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will be combin'd againſt the Devil's Temptation, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified againſt the flouts of thoſe that will <hi>think it ſtrange, that they
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:30773:31"/>run not with them in the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of riot.</hi> Eſpecially if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly obſerve the Second Duty, which is,</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Chriſtian Conference,</hi> the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants diſcourſing together about the things of God. Beſides your va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Hours in Winter Evenings, and when your Work is done, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts of your Work afford lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for Diſcourſe, yea, and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for ſpiritual improvement, if your Hearts will ſerve you. Some of you have more knowledge than others, and ſome more tender af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and how well would theſe Gifts be employ'd, if like <hi>thoſe that feared the Lord,</hi> Malac. 3.16. <hi>You ſpake often one to another</hi> about Soul-Affairs. Good Affections in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe do even naturally kindle the like in thoſe you are talking with: as Metal put into a Furnace is never melted ſo ſoon, as when added to ſome of the ſame Metal, melted before. <hi>As Iron ſharpens Iron, ſo
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:30773:31"/>does the Countenance of a Man, his Friend.</hi> How eaſily may two or three well-diſpoſed Servants carry away a whole Sermon in their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, when they ſhall repeat over the Heads to each other as they go along, or when they come home. This would make <hi>your hearts burn within you,</hi> and prepare you for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of your Maſters in the Family-Worſhip. But there are none ſo ſitted for <hi>Chriſtian Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> as they that can Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to each other, <hi>what God has done for their Souls.</hi> The School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſay, Angels of an Inferiour Order cannot enlighten thoſe of a Superiour. Sure I am the meaneſt Servant, that is truly Gracious, tho' of weak Parts and Gifts, may enlighten and warm by their hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Converſe thoſe that have great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Natural Endowments.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The other Duty is <hi>their ready helpfulneſs of each other, in all things wherein their aſſiſtance may be uſeful.</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:30773:32"/>Take each others concerns as your own, not as Buſie-bodies, but as helpers of them in their Work, when your Maſter's Service may be the better carry'd on. Let there be no fallings out amongſt your ſelves, no more than grumbling at your Maſters, that other Servants have leſſer work, or better uſage than you. Be as deſirous of their good as your own, and as ready to help them in any Sickneſſes or Straits, that your Fellow-Servants may be in, as you would be to be helpt your ſelves in the like caſe. And eſpecially rejoyce if you may be any ways helpful for their Souls. Some of them cannot Read, and you may teach them, and many ways further them in knowledge, or encourage any good Inclinations. When other Servants provoke one another to wrath, you muſt <hi>provoke</hi> your Fellow-Servants <hi>to love and good works.</hi> One Servant eaſily brings another to Inſtruction, by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:30773:32"/>Counſel and Example, and makes every Duty delightful by Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in it. And how ſweet is it for Servants to get into a Corner, and Pray together? What a Bleſſing will they be to one another, and to the Family and Neighbourhood where they Live?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Temptations and Hindrances of the Servants Calling. <hi>[1.]</hi> By being bred in Ignorance.</head>
               <p>THE Duties of Servants are of ſuch Importance, that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and a corrupt Heart will be ſure to lay in the way, or at leaſt to pretend many hindrances. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all Places and Callings have their Inconveniencies, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſuits his Baits not only to the inward Conſtitutions, but to their outward Conditions. He has one
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:30773:33"/>Wile for the Rich, and another for the Poor, one for the Maſter and another for the Servant. And as every one ſhould be acquainted with his Special Duty, ſo with the particular Temptations to which his place does expoſe him, and what Remedies the Word does preſcribe. I ſhall name three Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances of Servants more compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive than the reſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Firſt <hi>is Ignorance,</hi> the common ſnare of Countrey Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. Many of which, by the Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Careleſſneſs of their Parents, and Friends, cannot ſo much as Read, and tho' ſome would Charitably have paid for their Schooling in their Child-hood, they could not be ſpar'd from their Work. Many of them are of ſuch a rough Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and rugged temper, that they are <hi>as a wild Aſſes Colt,</hi> Job 11.12. and indeed this is the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of their caſe, that they are not only ignorant, but (as they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:30773:33"/>grew up) are affectedly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſo. Nay ſo far are ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſotted, that they make their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance their excuſe or pretence to caſt off all duty, and to oppoſe thoſe that would help them in it: they think it enough to ſay they are not <hi>Book-learn'd,</hi> or are <hi>no Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars:</hi> and though they were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with faculties capable of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and remembring the things of God, and in other things are wiſe for their age and breeding, <hi>yet the Oxe knows his Owner, and the Aſs his Maſter's Crib, but my people do not know.</hi> — Iſa. 1.2. Great is the compaſſion and condeſcenſion of God in revealing the myſteries of Religion to us. <hi>He has not dealt ſo with other Nations.</hi> He might have ſpoken his mind in lofty ſtrains, above the capacity of Creatures to conceive, but the neceſſary things are ſo plainly revealed, and eaſily remembred, that even Children have attained to great underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:30773:34"/>therein, and yet they are truths of ſo great moment, that the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Apoſtle deſpis'd all the <hi>wiſdom of this World</hi> in compariſon of the knowledge of Chriſt, nay, <hi>theſe things the Angels themſelves deſire to pry into.</hi> How frequently has this general ignorance been bewail'd, and the danger of it diſcovered to our careleſs Servants? How often has the cry of wiſdom been heard, <hi>How long you ſimple ones will you love ſimplicity, and ye fools hate knowledge?</hi> if you had had no means of Grace, nor Goſpel light, the caſe had been lamentable, Pro. 29.18. <hi>where there is no Viſion, the people periſh; but this is</hi> the <hi>condemnation that light is come into the World, and men love darkneſs rather than light,</hi> Joh. 3.19. if the word of Chriſt <hi>had not been ſpoken to you, you had not had ſin,</hi> in compariſon of what you have now, for <hi>now you have no cloak for your ſin,</hi> your conceitedneſs and obſtinacy. <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.39, 41. your ignorance is no
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:30773:34"/>leſs than direct enmity, and ſaying to God, <hi>Depart from us, we deſire not the knowledge of thy ways,</hi> Job 21.14. and how juſt will be the Sentence, for God to ſay to you, <hi>Depart from me, I know you not.</hi> Thus <hi>my people periſh for lack of knowledge,</hi> Hoſ. 6.4. and have that dreadful Curſe mention'd, <hi>Job</hi> 36.12. <hi>to dye without knowledge;</hi> and <hi>being a people of no underſtanding, He that made them will not have mercy upon them, and he that form'd them will ſhew them no favour,</hi> Iſa. 27.11. And <hi>when Chriſt ſhall be revealed in flaming fire to take vengeance on them that know not God,</hi> how will the Men of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh,</hi> of <hi>Tyre,</hi> of <hi>India,</hi> riſe up in judgment againſt thoſe that periſh in ignorance, from under Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and Calls of Grace therein?</p>
               <p>To remedy this ſore hindrance of all good, I exhort Servants,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Diligently to attend on the means of knowledge, and carefully to improve them.</hi> You do (at leaſt feemingly)
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:30773:35"/>attend on the preaching of the Word in the Publick Aſſemblies, but alas! To how little purpoſe, you eaſily perceive, when you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give the leaſt account of what you have heard, nor of the ſcope or drift of the plaineſt Sermons; and except in ſome few whoſe Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections being drawn out by a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, do afterwards ſeek after knowledge, we find by Experience, that Preaching, to thoſe that are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the firſt Principles, is like building without any Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion laid. God has appointed <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing</hi> as the ordinary means of Inſtruction in his Church, which you are called to ſubmit unto. And perhaps your Submiſſion to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry in this Ordinance, is the only poſſible way that knowledge is to be had for ſome of you. Are there not of you that live with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters as careleſs as your ſelves, from whom you ſhall not hear a ſerious word about God or Chriſt, from
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:30773:35"/>one end of the Week to the other? Which way can you expect to learn, if you refuſe our help? Think not that Catechizing is only for Children, when your ſelves <hi>are Children in underſtanding,</hi> and being grown in Years, have need to make the more haſt to learn. If you ſtay a little longer, it will be too late to teach you, nothing almoſt being more untractable than ignorant and ungodly Old Age. Will you defer being inſtructed till you have Families of your own, and have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to teach and inſtruct? Oh, do not multiply the number of Prayerleſs, Careleſs Families. I know the uſual Plea is, That you are aſham'd to anſwer, eſpecially before the Congregation. Indeed ignorance is matter of ſhame, but it is every where repreſented in Scripture as a lovely thing, to ſee young perſons forward in coming to Chriſt, and a great honour it is to be examples to others in ſeeking
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:30773:36"/>after inſtruction. It is a ſad thing that the Ordinances ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed as a matter of <hi>ſhame,</hi> and how then can you think of appearing before the greateſt Aſſembly at laſt? And what dreadful <hi>ſhame</hi> and confuſion of Face, will Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Souls be covered with then, when all your ſecret ſins ſhall be made manifeſt, and all your fooliſh hopes daſh'd, and God himſelf ſhall pour contempt upon you? It is true, it is better to come and learn privately, as <hi>Nicodemus by Night,</hi> than not at all; but a little uſe and experience of the good of it, <hi>will</hi> make Publick Catechizing delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to you. For indeed you muſt do what you do with a willing chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs: <hi>Let a Man account of us as Stewards,</hi> &amp;c. Now the Family run willingly to the Steward for their Food. And they that know what the Scripture means by <hi>digging for knowledge,</hi> will attend upon the means with conſtancy. For <hi>then
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:30773:36"/>ſhall you know if you follow on to know the Lord,</hi> Hoſ. 6.3. Suppoſing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that you practiſe what you know, for <hi>a good underſtanding have all they that do his Commandments,</hi> Pſ. 111.10.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The other remedy is <hi>to cry and pray hard for knowledge,</hi> and as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>to lift up your voice for underſtanding.</hi> Pray, and get others to pray for you — <hi>that you may be filled with the knowledge of his will, in all wiſdom and ſpiritual un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> Col. 1.9. that God would <hi>open your underſtandings,</hi> and then give light and knowledge thereunto, <hi>that the father of glory would give unto you the ſpirit of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and revelation in the knowledge of him, The eyes of your underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings being enlightned,</hi> Eph. 1.17, 18. that you may not only be taught of men, but, <hi>as it is written in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, may be taught of God.</hi> That you may not only have ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of Chriſt in your Minds,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:30773:37"/>of his Perſon, his Nature, his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, his Offices, and States of Humiliation and Exaltation; but that <hi>you may comprehend with all Saints what is the heighth, and length, and breadth, and depth of the love of Chriſt, and to know it, though it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth knowledge;</hi> that you may know him in his Beauty, his Fullneſs, his Willingneſs, his Preſence and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his love in your Souls; that you may ſo know him, as by Faith to come to him, receive and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him. Theſe are the things which he has promis'd to beſtow in the Covenant of Grace, and gives forth in a way of Prayer. Go to him as the <hi>Father of lights, who gives liberally,</hi> and <hi>will not upbraid,</hi> nor twit you with the ignorance in which you were bred, nor the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsneſs in which you liv'd ſo long.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:30773:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The hindrances of Servants calling <hi>[2.]</hi> by diſcontent and repining at their condition.</head>
               <p>THey that know little of God, have underſtanding ſufficient for their buſineſs in the World, but for want of ſaving Knowledge and Grace, how many poor Servants go on uncomfortably in it? they look upon themſelves as hardly dealt with, and are apt to fret and fume at the narrow Portion allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them by Providence, to be laid in ſome cold out-Houſe, or meaneſt Loft, of a poor Cottage, to have the leavings of the courſe fare there; hard work, cold blaſts abroad, and, perhaps, hard words and unkind uſage at home: this grates upon the Spirit, and makes them think their Life more miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:30773:38"/>than any others; and they that know not God, will talk like Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and rail at luck or Fortune, for placing them in ſuch mean cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. This makes them go heavily on, and their wrigling makes their Yoke to gaul them, and every part of the work uneaſy that they go about: they are apt to grudge at any one that goes finer, and (as they think) fares better, and that every one does them wrong, that does not ſweat as much as they; and if God be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by their fretting, they mind it not. He ſends them troubles and croſſes, which meeting with a proud unbroken Spirit, do cauſe them to tumultuate and murmure the more. Nor is diſcontent the ſin only of Servants, but of their Maſters and others; for it is not in the condition, but in the temper of their Spirits, till the heart be chang'd and cur'd. But I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuch remedies, as do particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:30773:38"/>reſpect the perſons to whom I am ſpeaking. It concerns All that lie under this temptation, to conſider the Soveraignty of God, and his Wiſdom in appointing their lot, that Nature is contented with a little, and Grace with leſs; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the loweſt condition out of Hell, is mercy to poor loſt Sinners, how eaſily God can change their lot, if he ſees it good, and how ſweet the loweſt ſtate may be made to them by Quietneſs, and Contentment. But there are two ſpecial Conſiderations that I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to Servants, in order to the removing this hindrance of their Duty, that from henceforth they may bear the Inconveniencies of their Callings, with a more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed mind, that they may not be weary of their condition, or irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely long for alterations of it; but may wait God s leiſure, and be kindly affected towards others that are in a higher condition in the World than they.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:30773:39"/>1. And the Firſt Conſideration is, <hi>The happineſs of the condition of Servants, in compariſon of that of many others.</hi> For not to compare you with the Miſerable Vagrants, that eat the Bread out of the Mouths of the true Poor; touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which diſorderly Perſons, we have the Apoſtle's Command, <hi>That if they will not work, they muſt not eat.</hi> I rather ſpeak of the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch as you never knew, or conſidered in your Diſcontent. How far then, has God ſet you above Servants in other Times and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which have been, and are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to Slavery, and forced Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the Luſts of Men. Of this ſort were many of thoſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to whom the Apoſtles wrote; and if they were to do their work <hi>heartily</hi> without grudging, how much more ſhould you? And in our Age have you never heard of the Slaves in the Plantations, and how they are us'd (eſpecially with
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:30773:39"/>reſpect to their Souls) by ſome more Savages than the Negro's that they call ſo? And what Servant in <hi>England</hi> dares repine at their ſtate, that has ever known the Condition of their own Countrey-men, when Slaves in <hi>Algiers,</hi> and other places: For not only are they enſlav'd in a ſtrange Countrey, whereas the Smoak of ones own Countrey, is ſweeter than the cleareſt Air in a ſtrange Land: but the Miſeries they ſuffer under Barbarous Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, calls for your pity towards them, and contentment with your merciful Lot. For being bereft un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly of all their Goods, they are conſtantly compelled to the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Labour, without any reſt, ſcarce to drink a little Water, and eat their decay'd Barly, and Broth of Camels, worn out with Work, like themſelves; and this with the only intermiſſion of four Days in the Year, upon the ſlighteſt Faults cruelly beaten, that they often die
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:30773:40"/>of their pain. Indeed their Lives are no further valu'd, than for their Service, or Slavery, and their Souls in greater danger, by continual Temptations to eſcape all theſe Hardſhips, by a dreadful Apoſtaſie. And to leave theſe to conſider ſome others, that ſeem to have a Life as full of Pleaſure, as theſe that I have mention'd have of Miſery; I mean the <hi>Servants of State,</hi> whoſe Life you ſo much envy for their Eaſe, and Fine Cloths. Did you but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their Temptations to Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and thereby to almoſt all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſins, you would ſee that God has delivered you from many ſnares, to which they are daily expos'd. By appointing you a moderate La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour (which is for the Health of your Bodies, and the good of the Publick) your Souls are not in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of flattering the Great, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring to the Pride and Luſts of thoſe, that think their Riches pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge them to live a Life of Sloth
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:30773:40"/>and Senſuality. Not that it is thus in all great Houſes, God forbid; but that it is very difficult <hi>for a Camel to get through the Eye of a Needle.</hi> And how general is the Debauchery, and Ruine of thoſe Servants, that at firſt you grudged at? But to come nearer home, how free is the Servants Life, and void of thoſe Troubles, to which even your own Maſters, and others that live round you, are frequently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd? They have great Rents to pay, and the Money hardly got to pay them with; they have Meat and Drink to provide for you, and Wages at the Years end; one tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſſes on their Fields, and another defrauds them of their Debts. They hardly bear their own wants, and more hardly the wants of Wives and Children: They have Loſſes to be made up abroad, and Houſes to be repair'd at home: And you ſee all this, but feel it not. You have no care (next to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:30773:41"/>the pleaſing God) but to do your work in the Day, and ſleep quietly in the Night. Are not theſe bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens on their Minds, greater than any you bear on your Shoulders? And to name but one thing more under this Head, Is there not a worſe ſervice, or ſlavery, than that I ſpeak of, in <hi>Algiers?</hi> Are there not Covenant-Slaves of <hi>Satan,</hi> that have ſold themſelves to work wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and made a kind <hi>of League with Hell?</hi> All that worſe than <hi>Egyptian Service, wherewith they are made to ſerve,</hi> Is it not <hi>with rigour?</hi> And though they are Lords and Ladies, and have long Trains of Servants, yet if they are Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, Are they not Servants? Yea, Bond-ſlaves to <hi>Sin, Satan, Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and the <hi>fear of Death? Let not thy heart envy ſinners.</hi> But this laſt Compariſon does reſpect the Godly Servants only, and ſo brings me to the ſecond Conſideration to cure this Diſcontent, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:30773:41"/>2. <hi>The much more happineſs of the Servants of God, though in the loweſt and meanneſt ſervices amongſt Men. As He that is called being free is the Lord's Servant: ſo He that is called, being a Servant, is the Lord's Free-man,</hi> 1 Corinth. 7.22. Though he ty'd faſt your Yoke by his Word, in all due Obedience to your Maſters; yet, having broke the Yoke of Sin, He has made you freer than Princes that continue under it. <hi>Whom the Son makes free they are free indeed,</hi> John 8.36. His <hi>Service is perfect Freedom,</hi> though your Service to Men ſhould be heavy to a Bondage. How pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a Liberty has Chriſt bought for you, and beſtow'd by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit upon you, if you belong to him, though the meaneſt Servant here in the loweſt Cottage! He has given you the external <hi>Liberty</hi> of his Houſe, admitted you to feaſt at his Table, given you free leave to partake of his Proviſion,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:30773:42"/>and appointed his Stewards to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence it accordingly, and <hi>whether Paul or Apollos or Cephas, all are yours.</hi> He has ſweetned this with a <hi>Liberty</hi> of Conſcience, and of a Judgment rightly inform'd: for though he has not delivered you from a ſubjection to Magiſtrates any more than to your Maſters; yet ſo free has he made you, That nothing ſhall bind your Conſcience but his own Word, and all your Obedience to the Commands of Men, ſhall be <hi>for Conſcience ſake</hi> towards God, requiring that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. But, above all, where <hi>the Spirit of the Lord is there is Liberty</hi> of Heart and Will in the work of your Maſter. Not a <hi>Liberty</hi> to live in ſin, which is an Abuſe of the word, and a <hi>Liberty</hi> that is not in Heaven it ſelf; the Perfections of God are an Eternal Law to himſelf, that <hi>he cannot lye,</hi> or <hi>deny himſelf;</hi> but an holy exemption from the Servility of Sin, and a
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:30773:42"/>free propenſion to whatſoever is good; that whereas before you could not pray, you were bound up and fetter'd, <hi>He has now brought you out of Priſon, that you may praiſe his Name.</hi> That under any temptation to diſcontent in the Service of Men, your Souls ſhould be raiſed in Praiſe of your Great Maſter, who has already entered you <hi>into the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God,</hi> and will at laſt ſet you at liberty from the burden of this fleſh, and the Body it ſelf, at the laſt day, from the hand of the Grave, and will make all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants <hi>Kings and Prieſts to God and our Father.</hi> Oh, <hi>bleſſed are thy Servants that ſhall dwell in thy houſe, for they will be ſtill praiſing thee.</hi> And bleſſed be his glorious Name, <hi>who took upon him the form of a Servant,</hi> and was himſelf bound to a Pillar, That he might ſet us free. Who <hi>has proclaimed Liberty</hi> by his Goſpel, <hi>and the opening of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:30773:43"/>doors to them that are bound,</hi> who has given us of his <hi>free Spirit.</hi> and <hi>made us willing in the day of his power, and here we offer up our ſelves, our Souls and Bodies as our moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Service. We thank thee, and praiſe thy glorious Name. But who am I, or what is my people, that we ſhould be able to offer ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly after this ſort? For all things come of thee, and of thine own have we given thee,</hi> 1 Chron. 29.13, 14. And let none repine at being Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, who through Grace, have ſuch a Liberty, and Freedom as this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:30773:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The Hinderances of the Servants Calling <hi>[3.]</hi> Want of Time, real or pretended.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TO every Work there is an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pcinted Time,</hi> and every Duty has the ſpecial Seaſon for it; but here lies the Servants difficulty, their Time is their Maſter's, and his Work fills it up, that they have not the leiſure for Duties and Exerciſes of Religion that others have. Others can read and pray as long as they will, but Servants are called up early about their Work, and tyred with it all day, and what time then have they for Prayer, Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or Covenanting with God? Truly, by the way, <hi>to whom much is given, of them God requires the more.</hi> And they that have Eſtates, and leſs neceſſary Buſineſs in the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:30773:44"/>World, muſt find more Time for the immediate Service and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, than the poor Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant can. But ſtill <hi>one thing is neceſſary,</hi> and they that have moſt Buſineſs in the World, have Souls to mind as well as others. Some, indeed, have Maſters that do pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely allow them time, and ſee that they ſpend it in Reading, and other Duties; and ſome, whoſe Hearts God has inclin'd by Grace, can find time to have their Hearts with God, when their Hands are in the World; and what ſweet and Heavenly Meditations does their Plowing, Sowing, Reaping, and other parts of their Work, afford them? Though they cannot be long at Prayer, they endeavour to be the more fervent in it; they go the more unwillingly from it, and come to it the more chearfully again. When they go into the Fields to their Work, or come back, they have as free a time, as
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:30773:44"/>if <hi>entered into a Cloſet, and the door ſhut about them.</hi> But it is not thus with all; ſome have rough and careleſs Maſters, that hurry them to bed, that they may riſe the ſooner about their Work, and think all time loſt when that is not in hand, and the ſlothful Heart is glad of the Excuſe, to ſilence Conſcience, which elſe would check them, for living without Prayer, and other Duties that they have heard preſs'd upon them: offer them a Catechiſm, they have no time to learn it; others go to an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for Inſtruction, but they cannot be ſpar'd to go with them. Like <hi>Faelix,</hi> they put it off <hi>to a more convenient time,</hi> which yet never comes.</p>
               <p>To remedy this ſore Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, there are theſe Two plain Directions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That they carefully avoid all thoſe things, that unneceſſarily and ſinfully take up their time,</hi> and then
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:30773:45"/>they will quickly ſind, That want of Time is more a pretended than real Hinderance of the Servant's Duty. To ſpeak plainly to you, How did ſuch and ſuch (whom you know, and perhaps have laugh'd at, as too preciſe) get their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the things of God? How do they get time for Prayer, and Reading, and Examination of their Hearts? Have not they as hard Places as you, and as much Work on their hands, and better done? Is it not that they redeem and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the time, that you trifie and ſquander away? Is it not known of ſome of you, That ſome mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Meetings (as they call them) and drunken Bouts, have firſt ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len away your Hearts, and then ſteal away your Time? And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you did not, it may be, come reeling home, you think it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that you have waſted the good Creatures of God, and the <hi>Time,</hi> which he lent you for high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:30773:45"/>Ends. Oh, how will this <hi>bite like an Adder</hi> when time ſhall be gone indeed, <hi>and the Angel ſhall lift up his hand, and ſwear by him that lives for ever and ever, that time ſhall be no more, and thou mourn at laſt, when thy fleſh and thy body are conſumed, and ſay, How have I hated Inſtruction?— and have not obeyed the voice of my Teachers, nor inclined mine ear to them that inſtructed me?</hi> Prov. 5.11, 12, 13. Do you think, That this Plea will hold at laſt, when all the Tribes of the Earth ſhall be gathered before their Judge, and you ſtand trembling amongſt the reſt? Shall it ſuffice to ſay, I heard indeed the Calls of Grace, but, Lord, I was a Servant, and had but little time? Will He not ſay, <hi>Out of thine own mouth I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thee, thou wicked Servant.</hi> Thou kneweſt that thou hadſt but a little time, why then didſt thou ſquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it away amongſt thy idle Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions?
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:30773:46"/>Why then didſt thou ſit up to ſuch unſeaſonable hours at thy Cards and other Sports? If thou doſt indeed want time, leave off thy Chat, thy idle Stories, that fill up the long Winter Evenings, and other vacant hours, and thou wouldſt have it. Yea, better that thou ſhouldſt work the harder, and ſleep the leſs, that thou mayſt get time for thy Soul, before Sickneſs and Death overtake thee, and thou cry in vain, <hi>Call time back again, Oh, call time back again,</hi> when it is too late, and thou art lanching into the Ocean of Eternity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That Servants that want time all the Week, <hi>do the more dearly prize the Lord's Day, and improve the Seaſons of Grace therein.</hi> When by God's Conſent you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted with your Maſters for your Time, this Day He reſerv'd for his own ſpecial Service. And that Maſters might know, That the Commandment about the Sabbath
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:30773:46"/>was for their Servants as well as themſelves, He adds this to the Law in one place— <hi>That thy Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant and thy Maid-ſervant may reſt as well as thou,</hi> Deut. 5.14. This is now <hi>the Labourers reſt,</hi> and ſee you loſe not a minute of ſo precious a time. Diſpatch your Buſineſs the ſooner the Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſhake off your Worldly Thoughts, and go ſeaſonably to reſt, that you may not lie abed longer on the Lord's Day Morning than at other times. Oh, think not (when you ſay, <hi>you want time</hi>) to keep a Sabbath in an outward ſlothful reſt, as your Horſes, and other Beaſts do. Meddle with no worldly Buſineſs on this Holy Day, but what is of Neceſſity; and count nothing of neceſſity that hinders the Work of the Day, and may be put off till another time. If you have Maſters that know the Worth of a Sabbath, they'll take care of you eſpecially
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:30773:47"/>on this day, not only to keep you from all Buſineſs that is not ſuited to the Day, but to put you upon all Holy Exerciſes therein; and how ſweet is it, to ſee Maſters come to the Publick Aſſemblies <hi>furniſhed with their Train,</hi> not ſuffering a Servant that can be ſpar'd, to ſtay at home, or lagg behind! And if you have careleſs Maſters, that would have you make your viſits, or go journies on this Day, becauſe they cannot ſpare you on another, rather deny your ſelves the Liberty offer'd you, than be depriv'd of the Dearer Liberty of the Houſe of God: Above all, avoid the prophane Feaſts that yet are kept up in ſome places on the Lord's Day. Let no Buſineſs of your own hinder you (where it may be) from attending Forenoon and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon on the Publick Worſhip, and that with Seriouſneſs and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, as thoſe that know into whoſe Preſence you are come: and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:30773:47"/>beg earneſtly for the Power of the Spirit to accompany the Word to your Souls. Do not think the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath is ended when the Sermon is done. Let no wicked Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons perſwade, That you may <hi>find your own pleaſures on this Holy Day,</hi> Iſa. 58.13. Remember what an Inlet Sabbath-breaking has been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Wickedneſs; how many wicked Servants, from cheating their Maſters, have been drawn to other Crimes, and on the Gallows confeſs'd, That neglecting and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning the Sabbath was the ſin that expoſed them to thoſe Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations which brought them thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Be you a <hi>Companion of them that fear the Lord,</hi> and if you have none ſuch to confer with about what you have heard, as you go home or when you come there, be the more by your ſelves: double all the Spiritual Duties now, that you have leſs time for on other days. Be ready to give an account
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:30773:48"/>of your profiting, if you are ſo happy, <hi>as</hi> to have Maſters that will examine you; and count not the Day, or the Duties therein, <hi>a Wearineſs,</hi> but <hi>call the Sabbath a Delight.</hi> Admire the Kindneſs of God to poor Servants, in appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Day on purpoſe for that, which elſe you could hardly have found time for. Look upon it as the Great Thankſgiving-Day, Praiſe him for all his wondrous Works; eſpecially, for your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by <hi>our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who, when He had finiſhed his Suffering-work, did riſe again from the Dead on the Firſt Day of the Week, and ſet his own Name on that Day; That they that are ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with their Labours all the Week, may reſt upon it; That the meaneſt of his People may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice therein, in hopes of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Sabbath above; where theſe Earthly Relations will ceaſe, and there will be no more Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:30773:48"/>of <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Servant;</hi> but all ſwallowed up in one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Relation, to Him, <hi>of whom the whole Family in Heaven and Earth is named,</hi> and in one Holy Service of Praiſe and Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <hi>to him that ſits upon the Throne, and to the Lamb for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
